<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "../../nlm/tax-treatment-NS0.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">63</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="index">urn:lsid:arphahub.com:pub:0E0032F455AE52638B3CF4DD637C30C2</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title xml:lang="en">Biodiversity Information Science and Standards</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">BISS</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2535-0897</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/biss.3.37439</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">37439</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">11036</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Conference Abstract</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="conference-part">
          <subject>SS48 Strengthening the biodiversity informatics community of practice through capacity enhancement</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>ecoEd: Cohesive training and skill development for digital ecoscience tools</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group content-type="authors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Huijbers</surname>
            <given-names>Chantal</given-names>
          </name>
          <email xlink:type="simple">c.huijbers@griffith.edu.au</email>
          <uri content-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5206-3415</uri>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line content-type="verbatim">Griffith University, Gold Coast, Australia</addr-line>
        <institution>Griffith University</institution>
        <addr-line content-type="city">Gold Coast</addr-line>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="corresp">
          <p>Corresponding author: Chantal Huijbers (<email xlink:type="simple">c.huijbers@griffith.edu.au</email>).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="edited-by">
          <p>Academic editor: </p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2019</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>06</month>
        <year>2019</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <elocation-id>e37439</elocation-id>
      <uri content-type="arpha" xlink:href="http://openbiodiv.net/60AD19CCF4BE519A88F8976E96693031">60AD19CCF4BE519A88F8976E96693031</uri>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>06</month>
          <year>2019</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Chantal Huijbers</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY 4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <label>Abstract</label>
        <p>Digital research infrastructures such as data portals and virtual laboratories enable easier access to data and analytical tools. Such infrastructures are essential to deliver research excellence that drives innovation, but we also need to ensure that we have a skilled workforce that can use these infrastructures. Therefore, training and skill development of students, researchers, government practitioners and industry professionals is key to the long-term success of this investment. In Australia, a suite of digital infrastructures has been developed for environmental sciences to enhance our understanding of the natural world and making forward projections into novel conditions (e.g. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ala.org.au/">Atlas of Living Australia</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bccvl.org.au/">Biodiversity and Climate Change Virtual Laboratory</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ecocloud.org.au/"><italic>ecocloud</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.tern.org.au/">Terrestrial Ecosystem Research Network</ext-link>). To provide users with a holistic approach to environmental spatial data discovery and analysis, these infrastructures have joined forces to deliver an exciting and innovative new training program. This program, called <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ecoed.org.au/"><italic>ecoEd</italic>,</ext-link> provides cohesive training and skill development to university lecturers, researchers and industry professionals enabling them to combine theoretical concepts with real-world applications.</p>
        <p>In this presentation, I will present how <italic>ecoEd</italic> was developed and the outcomes of the training sessions in which a group of <italic>ecoEd</italic> Champions absorbed ready-to-use lecture and workshop modules along with tools and knowledge on how to use the platforms. These resources can immediately be used in undergraduate courses that focus on topics such as ecology, biogeography, conservation biology, environmental management and spatial analysis as well as in stand alone workshops for researchers and practitioners. The training program aims to provide the Champions with the resources and knowledge required so that they can confidently re-deliver the lectures and workshops in their own institutions. As such, <italic>ecoEd</italic> is increasing the capacity of Australia’s environmental science community to advance science and deliver outcomes that underpin the sustainable use of our ecosystems using the latest advances in digital technologies. Moreover, it is enabling first-rate science education in Australia by supporting and nurturing our future scientists.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <label>Keywords</label>
        <kwd>training</kwd>
        <kwd>skill development</kwd>
        <kwd>platforms</kwd>
        <kwd>tools</kwd>
        <kwd>infrastructure</kwd>
        <kwd>biodiversity</kwd>
        <kwd>Australia</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <conference>
        <conf-date>2019</conf-date>
        <conf-name>Biodiversity_Next</conf-name>
        <conf-acronym>Biodiversity_Next 2019</conf-acronym>
        <conf-loc>Leiden, The Netherlands</conf-loc>
        <conf-theme>A joint conference by The Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF), a new pan-European Research Infrastructure initiative (DiSSCo),  the national resource for digitized information about vouchered natural history collections (iDigBio), Consortium of European Taxonomic Facilities (CETAF), Biodiversity Information Standards (TDWG) and LifeWatch ERIC, the e-Science and Technology European Infrastructure for Biodiversity and Ecosystem Research.</conf-theme>
      </conference>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="0"/>
        <table-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="0"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <sec sec-type="Presenting author">
        <title>Presenting author</title>
        <p>Chantal Huijbers</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Presented at">
        <title>Presented at</title>
        <p>Biodiversity_Next 2019</p>
      </sec>
    </notes>
  </front>
</article>
